All right, welcome back.
やあ お帰りなさい
Now we're doing a third part of the capstone project walk-through. I'm Erin.
では Capstone プロジェクトのチュートリアルの 3番目ですエリンです
I'm Steven.
スティーブンです
And so far, we looked at how to generate waypoints,
ここまで ウェイポイントの生成方法
how to make the car follow these waypoints
車にこれらのウェイポイントを通過させる方法を見てきました
and now we're looking at traffic light classification.
ここでは 交差点の分類について見ていきます
Yes and so in this node we're going to do, basically the publishing,
はい では このノードで行うことは 基本的に
the waypoints of the closest traffic light to us,
自分から一番近い信号のウェイポイントと状態をパブリッシュすることです
and the state and figuring out how to stop the car based on traffic lights.
そして 信号に従って車を停止する方法を見つけ出します
Cool. So this part you could actually
素晴らしいこの部分では
use a classifier that you build yourself using TensorFlow.
TensorFlow を使って自分で構築した分類器を実際に使用できます
Yes, you could. So in this walk-through,
はい できますこのチュートリアルでは
we're not going to go over building the model to classify the traffic lights,
信号を分類するモデルの構築については話しません
but we will go over the structure of the code for publishing the closest waypoint.
でも 一番近いウェイポイントをパブリッシュするコードの構造について見ていきます
Okay. Cool, let's go ahead and dive in.
問題ないようですいいですね では早速はじめていきましょう
So I'm opening the tl detector to that py.
私は tl_detector.py を開いています
And let's look at what it looks like when you first load it up.
最初にロードしたときに それがどのように見えるのかをお見せしましょう
So, let's look at my subscribers.
サブスクライバーを見てみましょう
I got the current pose at base_waypoints.
/current_poseと/base_waypointsを取得しています
Those are good things to have.
これらはあるといいものです
I got traffic_lights.
traffic_lights を取得しました
So, I can just use that data that the simulator is sending me to
分類器を使用する代わりに シミュレーターが送信するそのデータを使用して
figure out what the light state is instead of using a classifier, right?
信号の状態が何かわかるんですよね?
Sure. When you're working with the simulator and
はいシミュレーターを使用すると 信号機メッセージには
the traffic lights messages will have the state of the light, red, green or yellow.
信号の状態が 赤 青 黄のどれかがわかります
That one you won't have that of course on
もちろんこれは車にはないので、
the car and so you'll need to rely on classifier,
車ではクラシファイに頼る必要がありますが、
but for testing purposes,
でも テスト目的の場合
before you start working on the classifier,
分類器を使用する前に
you can just depend on information from the simulator.
シミュレーターからの情報に依存することもできます
Sounds like a good way to get started.
いいはじまりですね
I have traffic_waypoint and that's what I'm publishing,
traffic_waypoint があり それをパブリッシュしています
and I also have an image color.
また image color もあります
So what is that all about?
これはいったい何でしょうか
So image color is camera data that's coming in from the car's camera.
image color はカメラのデータで 車のカメラからきています
And for this walk-through I don't think we'll be using image color,
よって このチュートリアルでは image color は使用しないと思います
but we'll see, because we're not going to be using.
というのもそれは使用しないので でもまあ あとで
There's different types, right?
ちがうタイプがあるんですよね?
Yes.
はい
Something like a raw data,
生データのような
the raw image as well.
生イメージも
Yes. I believe the repo is setup to have you use image color in your classifier,
はいrepo は分類器で image color を使うようにセットアップされていると思いますが
but you might want to use image raw instead.
代わりに image raw を使う方法もあります
Any particular reason why?
理由は特に何かあるんですか?
When you have an image raw and then you
image raw があって 新しい color スキーマに変換すると
translate it to a new color scheme, you might lose data.
データを失う可能性があります
If you're building a classifier,
分類器を構築しているとき
the classifier doesn't have to visually see
分類器は 人が行うように特定の color スキーマを
any particular color scheme like a person would.
視覚で見る必要はありません
It's helpful to have as much data going into your classifier as possible.
分類器に情報が集まれば集まるほどそれにこしたことはありません
So we have some code right here to set up the classifier
ここに分類器をセットアップするコードがあります
and then also some callbacks like we usually have.
また 通常あるコールバックもあります
And that's where this light information is coming from this traffic callback,
また それがこの traffic callback から信号の情報がくるところで
and we have this image callback.
またこの image callback もあります
Looks like that's an important one
traffic lights get-light-state のこのプロセスと同じように
as well as this process of traffic lights, get-light-state.
それは重要なもののようですね
Yes. So what's going on in this code up top here,
はいでは この上の部分のこのコードはどうなっているのでしょうか
so every time we get an image coming in, what do we do with that?
毎回イメージが 1 つ入ってくると それをどうしているのでしょうか?
And it looks like we're getting this process_traffic_lights,
この process_traffic_lights を取得しているようです
which gives us the state and that light_waypoint.
これはstateとlight_wpを提供します
And we have this camera image that we're
このイメージではじめるなら
saving off from our message if we have this image to begin with.
メッセージから保存しているこの camera image があります
And then we also have this state.
それにこのステートもあります
And that's the state of the light based on the processing of the traffic lights.
それは process_traffic_lights をもとにした信号の状態です
Yes. We should probably dive into this first and see
はい最初にこれを詳しく見ていくべきですね
what kind of values the state primary can have.
ステートパラメータが使用できる値は何かを見ていきます
Let's check out the resulting code then and look at process_traffic_lights.
コードの結果を見て それから process_traffic_lights を見てみましょう
So here we have closest_light and this line_waypoint_ndex,
ここでは closest_light とこの line_waypoint_ndex があります
which is, they're both none.
両方とも none です
Okay, so we need to figure out what these values are.
そこでこれらの値が何かを把握する必要があります
So closest_light I think is going to give us the closest traffic light,
closest_light は一番近い信号機を提供するのだと思いますが
but each traffic light comes with a traffic line,
それぞれの信号機には車線があります
which is the stop_line for that traffic light.
それは 信号機の停止車線です
I think what we wanna do is get the index of the closest traffic line to us.
やりたいことは一番近い信号の停止線のインデックスを取得することだと思います
And I bet we could use something like a KD tree again and to figure that out.
そしてそれを把握するためにKDツリーのようなものをまた使用できるのだと思います
Yes. That seems like a good plan.
はいそれはいいプランのようですね
Let's look at the details of this.
これの詳細を見ていきましょう
If self.pose, if we have the pose of the car and also we have the stop_line_positions,
self.pose で車の向きが分かっているなら、stop_line_positionsは、
nice, we're just getting that from config.
よかったですね 設定から取得するだけです
So those are set up ahead of time, passed into this node.
それらは以前にセットアップされ このノードに渡されています
And we have this car's waypoint index
またcar_wp_idx があり それ
and that's from our friend the KD tree again. Is that it?
もまたお馴染みのKDツリーからですか？
Yes.
はい
Closest waypoint?
一番近いウェイポイントも?
Yes. So this, if you've watched the previous videos,
はいこれもです 前のビデオを見ると
we set up KD trees to search for the closest waypoints in.
KDツリーが一番近いウェイポイントを検索するようにセットアップしています
In section one, right?
セクション 1 ですよね?
Yes. Basically the same idea.
はい基本的に同じアイデアです
So we can re-use that code and then we got this diff value.
なので そのコードを再利用してこの異なる値を取得しました
So, it's the length of the self.waypoints, waypoints.
それは self.waypoints waypoints の長さです
Yes.
はい
To find the closest visible traffic light, if one exists.
もしあるなら 一番近い目に見える信号機を見つけるには
So I think the idea with this code is that we're just going to
このコードの考えは 一番近い信号を見つけるために
iterate through the list of traffic lights to find the closest one.
信号のリストが繰り返し使用されるということだと思います
So we start off with the difference as big as it possibly could be.
一番大きな違いがあるものから開始します
Which is like eight. I think we have eight intersections.
それは 8 のようです8 個の交差点があると思います
So it's not huge like base waypoints where maybe it's 1000 or more.
そのため それは 100 以上もあるベースウェイポイントのように大きくありません
So, it really wouldn't make too much sense
そのような小さいリストには
to use a KD tree with such a small list, I mean.
KD ツリーを使用する必要はあまりないです
That's fine they just.
それは別にいいのですが
It won't be that much of a game.
あまりメリットがありません
Yes. Let's find and just iterate over it.
はい見つけて何度もやってみましょう
So in our enumerator,
enumeratorには
we have this light and we have this i value enumerators state.
この信号とエヌメレーターの状態のi値があります
And we have this line that we're grabbing from the stop_line_positions.
また この"line"は"stop_line_positions"か得られます
So that gives us the line of, the traffic line. Yes.
そのため 車線を提供しますはい
So, I'm thinking that this is an x and
これが get_closest_waypoint からの
y value from that line from the get_closest_waypoint.
その車線の x と y の値と考えています
So we have that closest waypoint now and looks like we're looking at
その一番近くのウェイポイントがあり 一番近いウェイポイントと
a difference between that closest waypoint and the car's waypoint.
車のウェイポイント間の差分をみているようです
Yes, so we have basically the number of indices
はい 基本的に 私たちの車とウェイポイントと車線のウェイポイント間の
between our cars waypoint and the waypoint of the traffic line.
インデックスの番号があります
And if it's greater than 0,
また そのウェイポイントが車の前にあり
if that waypoint is in front of the car and d is less than diff,
diff より小さい場合 それは 0 より大きいです
which means it's not going over,
これは通り過ぎないまたは8個の異なる状態を通過したくない
or we don't want to go past our eight different states.
という意味です
Okay, so we're just trying to figure out what is the smallest diff,
OK 一番小さい diff がどれかということを見つけようとしています
of course, that's why we're doing that check right there.
もちろんそれが そこの信号をチェックする理由です
And then we can just set our closest_light to the light
line_waypoint_index の信号への closest_light を
in the line_waypoint_index to that temp_waypoint_index.
その temp_waypoint_index に設定できます
So a simple linear check to see which is the closest.
どれが一番近いのかについてシンプルな線形チェックを行います
Yes. So we can just loop through all of those and we'll hopefully come
はいそのため それらのすべてをループして 車の前方の
out with the closest traffic line in front of the car.
一番近くの道路車線がどれかわかるはずです
And then we can pass this to, if closest_light.
一番近い信号があると これを通過できます
Okay. So we actually set this now.
では 実際にいまこれを設定します
And the state is equal to get_light_state closest_light.
状態は get_light_state closest_light と同じになります
So we can just see what that state of the light is after we've grabbed the closest_light.
closest_light を取得するとその信号の状態がわかります
Let's go ahead and check that out and then this
やってみて
is the closest_index from looking at the KD tree.
KD ツリーから見て これが closest_index であるか見てみましょう
So that's the get_closest_waypoint.
これが get_closest_waypoint です
We have get_light.
get_light があります
Yes, get_closest_light.
はい get_closest_light
There we go.
どうでしょう
So if we scroll up it's right here. So this.
スクロールアップしていくと ここにありますこれです
Get light state.
信号の状態を取得します
Get_light_state. Yes. So get_light_state is initially set up
Get_light_state.はいGet_light_state は
to have you use your classifier.
自分の分類器を使用するために最初にセットアップされます
So you'll see in the comment in our code,
コードにコメントがあります
we return self-taught light classifier.get classification,
自分で学習する信号分類器に戻りますが
but for testing purposes as Erin mentioned earlier,
エリンが前に言っていたようにテスト目的で
the traffic lights come in from the simulator with the state already.
信号は状態付きでシミュレーターからきます
So you can just use light.state for testing.
そのため テストには light.state を使用できます
So that's pretty easy just to grab it from there.
それはとても簡単です ここからそれを取得するだけです
Interesting to have a function just for that.
それだけのために関数があるというのは興味深いことです
Yes. But I think once you use a classifier that function won't get more.
はいでも 分類器を使用するとその関数は何も取得しなくなります
Then it'll make a lot more sense to have that function.
そのため その関数を利用するのがもっと合理的になります
And then we're just returning that line_waypoint and the index of that.
その line_waypoint とインデックスを返しているだけです
So the waypoint index in the state of that light.
これが その信号の状態のウェイポイントのインデックスです
Yes and we return a negative one and a
はい その地点を過ぎると
trafficlight.UNKNOWN now if we get past that point.
負のものと trafficlight.UNKNOWN を返します
That's right. That part is pretty important right there.
そうですその部分はそこでとても重要です
Yes, so if you don't have a traffic light and you want to be returning negative one,
はい 信号機がなくて負のものを返したい場合
and if the state of the traffic light,
また信号機の状態が
if you detect a traffic light and you can't tell what its state is,
信号機を検出したけれど その状態がわからない場合
then you want to be returning a trafficlight.UNKNOWN.
trafficlight.UNKNOWN を返します
So what happens if it's unknown?
不明な場合は何が起こったのでしょうか
What's the car going to do?
車はなにをするのでしょうか
This depends.
これはさまざまです
So for this project,
このプロジェクトの場合
it's probably best if it's unknown,
不明な場合たぶんそれがベストです
or if you can't find the traffic light just to keep the car moving.
または信号が見つからない場合 車を動かしたままにします
We're going to test your car in
非常によく制御された環境で車をテストします
a very controlled environment and so if it rolls through the traffic light,
そのため 信号を通過する場合
we can still test the Drive-By-Wire system,
Drive-By-Wire システムをテストして
make sure that it's following waypoints.
それがウェイポイントに沿っているか確認します
In real life, you'd probably want to bring the car to a stop if it sees.
実世界では もしそれがわかった場合は車を停止したいと思います
Sounds safer.
その方が安全ですね
Yes, if it sees a traffic light and can't determine the state of the traffic light.
はい 信号がわかって その信号の状態が決められない場合
So we're doing that processing.
そのため それを処理しています
Let's work our way back up.
では もとの作業に戻りましょう
So now we have the state and we also have the waypoint of that light.
では 状態がわかって その信号のウェイポイントもわかりました
And now we can actually do a check.
そして いま実際にチェックできます
Is it negative one? If it's not, what are we going to do?
それは負のものですか?そうでない場合は 何をしますか
And so we have this state does not equal state.
この状態は状態と一致しません
So, can you explain to me what's going on there?
そこで何が起きているのか説明できますか
Yes. If we've stored
はい
the previous state of the light and every time an image comes into this callback,
信号の前の状態を格納し 毎回このコールバックにイメージが出てくる
or we go through this code,
またはこのコードを実施する
and if an image comes in and we've classed it,
イメージがきてそれをクラス化した場合
we've processed that image with
その信号でそのイメージを処理し
the traffic light and determined that the state has changed.
状態が変更していることを決定しました
Yes, so it's dynamically changing.
はい それは大きく変更しています
Maybe the state of the light is changed from green to yellow, or yellow to red.
信号の状態は 青から黄 または黄から赤に変更されます
So it's gone through some transition?
では 遷移を行っているのですか?
Yes. And so if that's happened,
はいもしそうなら
then we start into this counting system.
このカウントシステムを開始します
Counter, yes. We set that up and state is equal to state.
カウンター はいそれをセットアップして 状態は state と同じになります
So, it looks like we're trying to make sure that this light
よって 何かアクションを起こす前に この信号がきちんと統一されていてことを
is staying pretty consistent before we're taking any action.
確認しようとしているようです
Yes. Your classifier maybe a little
はい
bit noisy and maybe the lights changing and then changing again.
分類器にノイズが多いか 信号が何度も変わっているかもしれません
Like it's gone from green, to yellow, to red.
緑から黄それから赤というように
And so we want to make sure that the light is going to stay and.
そこで 信号がそのままであることを確認します
You want to be pretty certain.
またそれが正しいことも
Yes. Before we take any action.
はい何かアクションを実行する前に
So that looks like it's happening when the state count is greater than
大きいくなっていても
some threshold here and then we're saving the last state from what the state was.
最後の状態がなにかを保存しています
And, we're doing this check here.
そのため このチェックをここでしています
So light_waypoint equals light_waypoint
状態が trafficlight.RED と一致して負のものでない場合
if state is equal to trafficlight.RED else negative one.
light_waypoint が light_waypoint と一致します
Right. So when we publish the location of this traffic light,
分かりますねこの信号の場所をパブリッシュするとき
we're really only interested in red traffic lights.
関心があることは信号が赤の時だけです
Everything else we can continue driving through.
それ以外はすべて引き続き走行し続けれます
So, light_waypoint equals itself if
信号の状態が赤の場合
the state of the traffic light is red
light_waypoint がそれ自体に一致します
otherwise we want to keep the light_waypoint to be equal to negative one.
でないと light_waypoint が負のものと同じままにしようとします
Then that's our waypoint updater.
それは道路での"waypoint"のアップデーターであり、
One down the road doesn't try to update
赤信号以外の何かに基づいて
the waypoint velocities based on something other than a red light.
"waypoint"の速度を更新しようとしません
Really, we only need to try to stop the car if the light is red.
本当に 信号が赤の場合にのみ車を停止する必要があります
It's not necessary at all,
全く必要のないことですが
but you may be interested in modifying this logic
この理論を変更し また信号が黄色の場合にコードを更新することに
to also update the code if the light is yellow.
関心を持つかもしれません
Oh yes. Be more cautious,
ええ気を付けてください
prepare to stop and even look at its pose and then environment.
停止の準備 またその一旦停止 その環境
Or maybe adding extra acceleration to get through that yellow light.
黄色を通過するために もっと加速を追加する必要があるかもしれません
Yes. That would be fun.
はいそれが面白いところです
Could they try it out on the test lot with you?
テストロットでそれを試せますか?
Better to bring the car to a stop.
車を停止させる方がいいです
Okay.
OK
Then we're just publishing that light_waypoint,
その light_waypoint をパブリッシュしているだけですが
else we're doing what?
それ以外に何かしていますか
We're also publishing the last waypoint and then state count plus one for our counter.
最新のウェイポイントもパブリッシュして 状態はカウンターに +1 をカウントします
Cool. So that's all getting set to the waypoints themselves.
素晴らしいそれはすべてウェイポイント自体で設定されます
So we're just publishing the index that we found and the light waypoint?
みつかったインデックスとその信号のウェイポイントをパブリッシュするだけですか
That's right and then later,
そのとおりです その後
we'll actually get to put use to it.
実際に put がそれを使用するようにします
Yes, so in the waypoint updater,
はい ウェイポイントアップデーターでは
the final part of this walkthrough,
このチュートリアルの最後の部分で それがわかったら
we'll discuss what to do with that light_waypoint once we've found one.
その light_waypoint  をどうするかを話し合います
Okay. Is there anything else you want to bring up with this part?
わかりましたこの部分で何か言いたいことはありますか
No. I think that's it.
いいえ これで全部です
Awesome. Alright.
素晴らしいできました
Alright. Thanks for joining us.
それでは参加してくれてありがとう